Boston, Mass. Union Congregational Church records, 1822-1984.
Congregational Library & Archives
Boston, Mass. Union Congregational Church records, 1822-1984.
RG0031
Congregational Library & Archives
3.27 Cubic Feet
(3 boxes, 2 folders)
The history of the Union Congregational Church begins with the formation of the Essex Street Church in 1819. In 1822, owing to a disagreement with the church's pastor, a minority of the church withdrew from the Essex Street Church and reformed the Union Congregational Church. The church was substantially rebuilt in 1840 and a new church building was constructed at the corner of Columbus Avenue and West Newton Street in 1870. In 1907, the Berkley Temple Congregational Church merged into the Union Congregational Church. In 1948, the Union Congregational Church merged into the Old South Church. This collection contains the administrative and membership records of the Union Congregational Church and includes meeting minutes, financial ledgers, legal documents, vital records, and records of church activities.
Union Congregational Church (Boston, Mass.)
Restrictions on Access
Access to this collection is unrestricted and open to the public.
Acquisition Information
Materials were initially donated to the Congregational Library & Archives at an unknown date; no accession number. The volume of worship programs was donated by Hubert E. Beckwith in March, 2019; 2019-22. Additional materials related to the merger between the Union Congregational Church and the Old South Church were acquired in an accrual of materials from the Old South Church; 2022-13.
Historical Note
The history of the Union Congregational Church begins with the formation of the Essex Street Church in 1819. The church was first formed in Boylston Hall and then moved to the Essex Street location which was constructed later in 1819. In 1822, owing to a disagreement with the church's pastor, James Sabine, the majority of the congregation returned to the Boylston Hall with Sabine to reform as the Essex Street Presbyterian Church. A minority of the church remained with the church building on Essex Street. With financial support from the Old South Church and Park Street Church, and new members transferring from the Old South Church, Park Street Church, and a church in Braintree, the Union Congregational Church was formally organized in 1822.
Samuel Green was installed as the first minister at the Union Congregational Church in 1823. During his pastorate, which ended in 1834, approximately 600 new members were added to the church's membership. In 1826, along with the Old South Church and Park Street Church, the Union Congregational Church helped to erect the Hanover Street Church, whose first minister was Lyman Beecher. In 1827, eighteen members of the Union Congregational Church agreeably split with the church to help form the Pine Street Church.
The church was substantially rebuilt in 1840. In 1868, the church's prudential committee was empowered to buy land at the corner of Columbus Avenue and West Newton Street. Construction on a new church building was completed in 1870. In 1907, at the recommendation of an ecclesiastical council, the Berkley Temple Congregational Church, whose history began with the formation of the Pine Street Church in 1827, merged into the Union Congregational Church.
Demographic changes to the South End of Boston caused major financial hardship for the Union Congregational Church throughout the first half of the 20th century. The Old South Church provided significant financial assistance during this time, however, by 1948, it was clear that the church could not remain solvent. In 1948, the Union Congregational Church merged into the Old South Church.
Ministers of the Union Congregational Church
Samuel Green 1823-1834
Nehemiah Adams 1834-1878
Henry M. Parsons 1870-1874
Frank Warfiel 1876-1881
R. R. Meredith 1883-1887
Nehemiah Boynton 1888-1896
Samuel Lane Loomis 1896-1907
Allen A. Stockdale 1907-1913
Ernest Graham Guthrie 1914-1925
Herbert A. Jump 1927-1932
Dwight J. Bradley 1934-1937
Fred D. Bennett 1938-1944
Ferdinand J. Loungway 1945-1948
Scope and Contents
This collection contains the administrative records of the Union Congregational Church, in Boston, as well as records of the church's membership and church activities. The collection contains administrative meeting minutes, vital records, such as records of marriages and baptisms, membership lists, financial documents and ledgers, legal documents and deeds, church histories, records of two church auxiliary groups, and select Sunday service programs.
Arrangement
This collection has been arranged into the five series listed below. Materials within each series have been arranged primarily by chronological order and secondarily by topic, when appropriate.
Series 1: Church records, 1822-1984
Series 2: Pew records, 1822-1905
Series 3: Financial and legal records, 1840-1949
Series 4: Membership records, 1876-1973
Series 5: Histories and programs, 1906-1945
Related Materials
The Congregational Library & Archives holds the Boston, Mass. Pine Street Church records, 1827-1907, RG0029, collection. The Pine Street Church was gathered in 1827, partially by members drawn from the Union Congregational Church. In 1907. The Pine Street Church, renamed the Berkeley Temple Congregational Church, merged into the Union Congregational Church.
The Congregational Library & Archives holds the Boston, Mass. Old South Church records, 1659-2012, RG0028, collection. The Old South Church provided significant financial assistance to the Union Congregational Church during the early 20th century and in 1948 the Union Congregational Church merged into the Old South Church.
Bibliography
The One Hundredth Anniversary of the founding of Union Church, Boston, 1922. Boston: 1922. 17.11.1 B65.5 UniCB
Baptismal records.; Christian union.; Church finance.; Church membership.; Church records and registers.; Legal documents.; Marriage records.; Pews and pew rights.; Worship programs.; Berkeley Temple Congregational Church (Boston, Mass.); Boston (Mass.) -- Church history.; Essex Street Church (Boston, Mass.); Old South Church (Boston, Mass.); Union Congregational Church (Boston, Mass.)
- Church records, 1822 1984; 1822-1984; 11 Volumes; 14 Folders
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains records related to the operation and administration of the Union Congregational Church. Included within the series are meeting minutes, reports, committee records, by-laws, and records related to the merger of the Union Congregational Church into the Old South Church. This series also contains some records of the Union Church's Women's Association and the Corner Stone Class for Men.
  - Index to church records, 1822 1828; 1822-1828 (Box 2, Volume 1)
  - Church records, 1822 1844; 1822-1844 (Box 2, Volume 2)
  - Church records, 1844 1882; 1844-1882 (Box 2, Volume 3)
  - Church records, 1882 1915; 1882-1915 (Box 2, Volume 4)
    Separated Materials
    The Declaration of trust, 1888, was removed from this volume and foldered separately for preservation.
  - Church records, 1915 1927; 1915-1927 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Church records, 1927 1936; 1927-1936 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Church records, 1927 1948; 1927, 1948, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Materials in this folder were removed from the volume of Church records, 1936-1948, from between pages 98 and 99, for preservation purposes.
  - Church records, 1936 1948; 1936-1948 (Box 1, Volume 6)
    Materials were removed from between pages 98 and 99 of this volume and placed in the folder titled Church records, 1927, 1948, undated, for preservation purposes.
  - Standing committee records, 1883 1894; 1883-1894 (Box 1, Volume 1)
    Materials were removed from between pages 66 and 67 of this volume and placed into a new folder titled Church and standing committee meeting minutes, 1888, for preservation purposes.
  - Church and standing committee meeting minutes, 1888 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Materials in this folder were removed from the Standing Committee records, 1883-1894, volume, between pages 66 and 67, for the purposes of preserevation.
  - Standing committee records, 1895 1909; 1895-1909 (Box 1, Volume 2)
  - Standing committee records, 1909 1922; 1909-1922 (Box 1, Volume 3)
    Materials were removed from between pages 230 and 231 of this volume and placed in the folder titled Standing committee meeting requests, 1922, for preservation purposes.
  - Standing committee meeting requests, 1922 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Materials in this folder were removed from between pages 230 and 231 of the volume of Standing committee records, 1909-1922, for preservation purposes.
  - Standing committee records, 1922 1940; 1922-1940 (Box 1, Volume 4)
    Materials from the volume were removed to the folder titled Standing committee letter to Massachusetts Congregational Conference and Missionary Society, undated, for preservation purposes.
  - Standing committee records, 1940 1949; 1940-1949 (Box 1, Volume 5)
  - Declaration of trust, 1888 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    This item was removed from the Church records, 1882-1915, volume for the purposes of preservation.
  - Board of deacons responsibilities, 1901 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Corner Stone Class for Men records, 1908 1925; 1908-1925 (Box 1, Volume 9)
  - Corner Stone Class for Men records, 1914 1921; 1914-1921 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Standing committee rules, 1927 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - By-laws, 1929, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Annual meeting, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Union Church's Women's Association prospectuses, 1937 1944; 1937-1944 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Miscellaneous merger and historic documents, 1948 1984; 1948-1984 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Standing committee letter to Massachusetts Congregational Conference and Missionary Society, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Materials in this folder were removed from the volume of Standing committee records, 1922-1940, for preservation purposes.
- Pew records, 1822 1905; 1822-1905; 2 Volumes; 4 Folders
  This series contains pew deeds, pew records, and pew diagrams for the Union Congregational Church.
  - Pew plan, 1822 (Folder 1)
  - Pew plan, 1841 (Folder 2)
  - Pew deeds, 1843 1848; 1843-1848 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Pew deeds, 1869 1884; 1869-1884 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - List of pew holders, 1905 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    Materials in this folder were removed from the volume List of names of assigned sittings and locations, undated, for preservation purposes.
  - List of names of assigned sittings and locations, undated (Box 2, Volume 8)
    Materials were removed from this volume and placed into the folders titled Pew diagram, undated, and List of pew holders, 1905, for preservation purposes.
  - Pew diagram, undated (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Pew assessments and taxes, undated (Box 3, Volume 9)
- Financial and legal records, 1840 1949; 1840-1949; 8 Volumes; 25 Folders
  This series contains financial and legal records for the Union Congregational Church. The series contains ledgers, records related to bequests and various funds, a ledger for the Sabbath school, receipts, and mortgages. The series also contains financial and legal records related to the merger of the Union Congregational Church into the Old South Church.
  - Miscellaneous financial records, 1840 1852; 1840-1852 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Miscellaneous financial records, 1840 1852; 1840-1852 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Miscellaneous financial records, 1841 1854; 1841-1854 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Church fund record book, 1841 1929; 1841-1929 (Box 3, Volume 1)
  - Church funds account book, 1841 1873; 1841-1873 (Box 3, Volume 2)
  - Church funds account book, 1873 1916; 1873-1916 (Box 3, Volume 3)
  - Bills paid, 1843 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Vouchers for payment, 1845 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Bills paid, 1846 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Bills paid, 1847 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Bills paid, 1848 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Bills paid, 1849 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Bills paid, 1850 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Bills paid, 1851 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Bills paid, 1852 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Bills paid, 1852 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Bills paid, 1853 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Bills paid, 1854 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Mortgages, 1882 1888; 1882-1888 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Treasurer's report, 1884 1889; 1884-1889 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Indenture, 1887 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Berkeley Temple trust deed, 1902 1942; 1902, 1907, 1942 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Treasurer's ledger, 1907 1912; 1907-1912 (Box 3, Volume 4)
  - Treasurer's ledger, 1907 1914; 1907-1914 (Box 3, Volume 5)
  - Treasurer's ledger, 1913 1920; 1913-1920 (Box 3, Volume 6)
  - Treasurer's ledger, 1914 1920; 1914-1920 (Box 3, Volume 7)
  - Old South Society grant applications, 1909 1941; 1909-1941 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Sabbath school ledger, 1914 1921; 1914-1921 (Box 3, Volume 8)
  - Corporation document, 1915 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Bequests, 1936 1940; 1936-1940 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Sara D. Lane trust records, 1941 1950; 1941-1950 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Old South Church merger legal documents, 1948 1949; 1948-1949 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Legal records, 1948 1949; 1948-1949 (Box 3, Folder 14)
- Membership records, 1876 1973; 1876-1973; 4 Volumes; 4 Folders
  This series contains vital records related to the members of the Union Congregational Church. The series contains baptismal records, marriage records, and lists of church members.
  - Membership records, 1876 1948; 1876-1948 (Box 2, Volume 5)
    Materials in this volume were removed to the folder titled Assorted Sunday programs, 1926-1939, undated, for preservation purposes.
  - Membership list, 1886 1948; 1886-1948 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Baptismal records, 1892 1948; 1892-1948 (Box 1, Volume 7)
    Materials were removed from this volume and placed into the folder titled Baptismal inquiries, 1959-1973, for preservation purposes.
  - Membership list, 1894 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Vital records, 1895 1948; 1895-1948 (Box 2, Volume 6)
  - Membership list, 1907 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Marriage records, 1912 1948; 1912-1948 (Box 2, Volume 7)
  - Baptismal inquiries, 1959 1973; 1959-1973 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Materials in this folder were removed from the volume of Baptismal records, 1892-1948, for preservation purposes.
- Histories and programs, 1906 1945; 1906-1945; 2 Volumes; 3 Folders
  This series contains records relating to the history of the Union Congregational Church and programs for worship and special events held at the Union Congregational Church.
  - "Items of Union Church History", 1906 (Box 1, Volume 8)
  - Assorted Sunday programs, 1926 1939; 1926-1939, undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
    Materials in this folder were removed from the volume Membership records, 1876-1948, for preservation purposes.
  - History speeches, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - "Snap-shots of 1939" (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Sermons and special programs, 1942 1948; 1942-1948 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Worship programs, 1944 1945; 1944-1945 (Box 3, Volume 10)